Joey stop hmm so how does one lose
recollecting this so let's start by
reminding ourselves what their
politeness is so how would you how do
you collect yourself right now don't do
that
recollect remember what the basis for
this experience which might be you know
I generally I'm going to soap regularly
whether in re product yourself what will
you do potting body for example so you
would recollect something that's already
there yes on its own that's right which
is why the Buddha referred to it as a
reference point yeah the references for
your mindfulness sorry recollect this is
more like just understanding something
recognizing the reference point yes
understanding recognizing that which can
serve as a reference point which is your
body so practically speaking or you
might be mindful so you remember that
your body is there and then you can need
to send it further and see all this body
is a necessary basis for any one other
experience I can have but the point is
you don't need to be looking at the
specific experiences or even looking at
the body you just need to remember that
the body needs to be there as a basis
for whatever you are in currently
attending to and engage with and the
only reason that you would forget that
is because you haven't understood well
so that's that's my next question are so
if recollecting is the reference point
of your recollection is not created body
cannot be created by because you not my
body is real only when I attended to
know the body is there which is why you
can attend it too
which is why you don't have to attend it
too yeah you can just know it to the
extent necessary for the final knowledge
as it would I would say so if the
reference point is not in you how can
you lose your mindfulness then by
thinking that the reference point is in
you but misunderstanding by not
understanding the nature of of the body
the body of the reference point yeah by
being doubtful about it yeah
so in how would a doubt set in so say
now you're mindful your recollected of
the body and then you forget about it
but does that change where the body is
now does that change the nature of the
model itself
does that change anything that can arise
on the body as its basis impossible what
is the only thing that could change are
you forgetting the correct reference
point are you forgetting let's lecture
this if you're not forgetting the
reference point so you cried through the
greatness currently yeah you're becoming
more familiar with the nature of the
body yeah with its characteristic you're
allowing it to enjoy and that's as it is
which means you get to see it for what
it is yeah
to the extended City for the final
knowledge so forgetting about it is then
within the reference point of your
mindfulness yeah so forgetting about
things it's not how you lose my friends
it cannot be no it's because if
anything's wrong : yeah see the book
when people think that when I forget
about my body that's how stop being
mindful of the body they still think
that the mindfulness is rooted in them
attending to things in them being the
center of experience not in finding the
right reference point out there already
enduring him so for as long as you hold
on to the view that you are the center
of your experience which is already full
of conceit you don't understand what
mindfulness is understanding the
mindfulness is independent of you
because of these reference points of the
body feeling thoughts and the mind mind
and the thoughts means sense of self
like self center point of view is within
that it's not first it's not that which
determines it is that which is
determined by which I mean you can
forget all you want your mindfulness
remains undiminished yeah and that's
when you know your mindfulness is
perfected when forgetting about it does
not induce non recollect earnest because
it cannot but until you know that that's
basically the reason for you losing
regular yes not having clarity regarding the
yes not having clarity regarding the
nature of mindfulness not understanding
it because doesn't matter how much you
forget you cannot lose knowledge through
forgetting that which has been
understood becomes impenetrable becomes
indifferent to whether you think about
it or not whether you get distracted by
something else or not the things you
understood you don't need to keep
telling to yourself and repeating in
order to keep that understanding because
the understanding has taken place you
saw some you've used the example before
if you know how to draw it you don't
have to yeah think about driving every
individual could notice and I cry right
but if you don't attend to that skill
yeah but knowledge thing no it's clear
yes that's what it's meant to practice
to do joy marry me that's what it's
meant to practice to the extent
necessary for the final knowledge so
you're not practicing mindfulness for
its own sake you're practicing
mindfulness for the sake of this passion
this disenchantment letting go of the
world which means the point will come
when you have practiced mindfulness to a
sufficient degree that there is no more
basis for any passion to be maintained
your experience and that's when your
another hunt and yes you can stop
practicing mindfulness then but that's
kind of impossible because by that time
you already it wasn't your practice
anymore he was simply your knowledge but
you're saying so the basically the
knowledge that you're talking about the
knowledge of mindfulness or the
knowledge of the body
is beyond the threshold whereby if you
forget about it yeah it's it's it that's
not an issue that's not it's
impenetrable by your forgetfulness yet
because you understand the thought
forgetting is still on the basis and
then furthermore you get to understand
that your lap singing your mindfulness
did not start when you forgot about it
yeah it started when you remembered your
body again on a completely different
terms you remembered with confusion remember
you remembered with confusion remember
will mother remember without oh is this
the same is it different is it same or
different is it neither is this the same
feeling or let me start again
you can't start again because you
haven't started in the first place you
can only find things being there so you
can only continue but see you
prioritizing your idea of what
mindfulness is and what did my reference
my attending to things that's where
things originate that's how it comes to
be first means you would actually know
the fact that thing is already there
enduring so you wouldn't be discerning
it on its own terms you'll be molding
editing what you think it should be and
that's when you lose your a
collectiveness when you get back to the same thing with
when you get back to the same thing with
confusion with lack of understanding and
lack of clarity not when you forget
about it lack of clarity yeah so how to
maintain clarity you maintain clarity by
understanding the the reference point
because then clarity is is it is nothing
to do with what do you think about it or
not whether you're distracted by
something else or not the clarity of the
understood phenomenon understood nature
of mindfulness of the body remains the
same and the more you develop it means
the harder for you will be to be
confused about it let any clarity can be
developed so that yes it steady
it's clear yes well what do you mean by
all the time as long as you are
attending attending no that's not a
clarity clarity of understanding not
clarity of you attending to it it's the
opposite it's the opposite when you are
attending to something that's not your
mindfulness mindfulness is the reference
point that enables you to attend to it
to care about the context exactly so the
clarity of the context is what the
clarity of mindfulness is not the
clarity of your moment to movement
attention which is the result of the
whole context
did you now sacrifice on a kind of
prioritizing which you are staring at
can we also say that losing mindfulness
you lose recollecting this modular
forever you lose it by not seeing the
sameness I was gonna come to there now
look so let's take another for example
reference point of the feelings so what
is your current feeling now overall
fundamentally okay pleasant agreeable so
now we carry on talking and you forget
about now see when you recollect the
feeling you can't have a thought of what
your car in the feeling but you don't
need to attend to it in order to keep
feeling it it's the other way around
the only reason you can attend to it is
because it's felt already
thus you can turn your attention towards
it and you don't want to be dependent on
your attention equally mindfulness
because it's actually secondary to the
presence of the thing that you already
kind of know you want that knowledge
that you already have to start equaling
mindfulness so say you get distracted
you start thinking about something else
and now you want to reestablish your
ring collectiveness and you ask yourself
what am I feeling now and you say
feeling Pleasant what is your attitude
towards that reference point that you
rediscovered will determine whether your
mindfulness lapsed or whether it's still
the same enduring that has now included
the attitude of forgetting this
particular thing
so when you get back to the feeling now
after having been thinking about it do
you think it's a different feeling easy
the same feeling do you have any idea
where it was while you were not thinking
about it yeah what was it while you're
not thinking about it disappear and then
come back the same thing so was it still
there enduring so the feeling the
reference point of mindfulness can
endure then unchanged in its identity so
to speak without needing you to attend
to it constantly my feeling this of
feeling this and feeling feeling
touching touching moving moving you
don't need to keep repeating that yet
it's there and that's all in the
beginning of the knowledge next time
you'll be less wound up when you forget
about things and you will not try to
restart your entire practice you'll just
know I just need to recollect it
correctly because it was always there or
if you find out a different feeling it's
only different in its content yes that
nature of feeling remains the same and
enduring and that's the whole point so
it's how you recollect it determines
whether there is there is the right
context being established or not not
whether you forget about it or not your
knowledge remains yes and it's their
knowledge that you get to develop layer
by layer by layer but the knowledge
remains the same thing because it's not
expanding on you because everything that
has this anticipate that feeling or
let's say the nature of feeling remains
yes yeah that's where the knowledge is
yeah not to whether you attend to it or
not so the knowledge gets developed hmm
consciousness gets understood as the
Buddha said
I think the tendency for those people is
to prioritize their point of view change
so so you might have you might recognize
how careful how's it feeling now I had I
was being Pleasant all morning
but isn't the tendency I think is to put
first that what's changed
yeah well it's it because it's it's
rooted in that view that you can
impartially externally observe your
experience without being the partaker in
it or rather at the same time while
you're partaking in it you can have this
completely independent point of view
upon your experience point of view
that's independent of your experience
which the idea of science which is the
idea of common are they open people's
everything is impermanent it does I am
impermanent yeah so that's where people
who then just even when there is the
same feeling enduring they could not
bear they could not understand the idea
of a thing enduring unchanging yeah they
wouldn't say well it can't be the same
feeling cuz six seconds have passed yeah
and in my view every second is a
different entity but then if you were to
pursue their view are you realize it
contains a contradiction because there
is a millisecond with him I'm gonna say
I'm so how can you even after a word and
designate identity of something if it's
changing in every like those tiny
microscopic levels but they're calm
being and something enjoying the said
the comma sameness but other also being
changed a couple so I was gonna say that
that the point is not like almost it's
not about denying the fact that things
endure for five seconds or 10 seconds
its to recognize that it's your notion
of the thing comes first which is why
you can discern the endurance of it as
in its particular change if there is no
unifying identity of that finger the
change would not be perceivable and I
think that's what the mistake is that
people do first exercise their people
prioritize the mortgage angular yes the
particular has been which have changed
which is also hanging us in front that
is like the kind of first thing you see
the fit exactly yeah and you will remain
on that level there will always be the
first thing you see for as long as you
or
so bitching FL of sensuality but you can
it's also first thing you see sense
object you don't see sense restraint but
those so you have to learn how to look
at the periphery like like look at the
background because those those
particular changes can only be
particular changes of a thing you just
need to find the reference point then
remains the same throughout this change
just for mindfulness sense and not try
to reinterpret the reference point
through the change but try to understand
the change to the reference point yet
and so you can say oh this morning I
felt like this then I felt like that and
he said something else's name is this
tonight and it what was unchanged and
through that he was oh the something
that I the fact that my body was there
presence of my body was unchanged so
what is unchanged through all the
different postures all the different
bodily actions presence of the body is
unchanged which is exactly why you can
discern all this particular like exactly
sub general more particular changes but
no you choose to put that first and say
that I have the body because of all of
these molecular changes in constant
elements that I can only observe because
I have the body first yes
this reductionism like everything can be
reduced to there was many people try to
understand the nature through the same
kind of lens saying here look everything
is gone look things disappear does their
impermanent that's already burning
so impermanence is only to be discovered
when things are not disappeared while
you're still alive that the other way
you can understand it permanent so that
wait for death to be proof of
impermanence it's too late and it's not
a permanent spot work it's just another
change yeah so you're not freeing
yourself from the fact that things will
disappear you feel yourself that you're
constantly within the change and
partaking in to change and you will for
as long as you put that first and don't
see the nature of that which is changing
so the endurance is in a completely
opposite direction it's in that sorry
impermanence is and in different
directions in the direction of what is
actually enduring what's remaining the same in
enduring what's remaining the same in
yes exactly you say nice now say it
sounds like a contradiction sounds like
but that's exactly where it's very new
that's where the soda burners inside is
whatever has the nature of manifestation
that is why it's impermanent not because
I also waited long enough to see it
disappear no it's because it's right
there and I get to see it and because
that nature's present I get to
understand it yeah because cessation is
manifested as the Buddha said arising is
manifested cessation is manifested
impermanence is on the level of
manifestation and so seeing that the
nature of body as being so it's
basically it's already enduring whether
I attend to it or not so nothing to do
where do I forget about it or I don't
forget about it not gonna sued me so the
nature of that thing has nothing to do
with me because I have no control over
it that's why I mean if I keep putting
that first I will gradually undermine my
own gratuitous sense of that I first I
am the master controller of this body
that's the development yeah exactly
development of the nature think they
would reason have to result in this
passion
they keep saying in previous talks no
dog come back to the present moment
you couldn't have left it even if you
wanted it but the idea that you hold the
view that you can return implies that
you can leave so come back to the body
if you still subscribe to the view that
you can come back to it it carries the
implication that you could have left and
for as long as you hold the view you'll
never understand whether you leave or go
you are dependent on the body right
there so if your practice is to keep
returning to the present moment you are
intentionally maintaining your wrong
view that you can leave the present
removing yeah assuming with you can you
which ironically keeps you away from the
present moment yeah but it's like when
you are recollected it's not about
attending to the body here it's more
like understanding the body that is here
understanding the feeling that is here
understanding the mind that is here
understanding that the thoughts that are
here there's a necessary basis for
everything else that I can attend on
account of it so you said yeah yeah not
interested to be developed consciousness
to be understood yeah it's the same
thing yeah conscious state consciousness
as the aggregate is the soap because
usually consciousness is where my point
of view is but then you realize
understanding that there is no such
thing is an independent point of view
independent of the existing body in the
existing feeling existing my an existing
thoughts means there is no such thing as
consciousness independent of the
existing matter and everything else so
your sense of self yourself sentiments
nobody denies that it's there but you
see it now second which means that's not
the own and that's not the master it's
it's when these things disappear my
sense of self cannot remain that
basically experience of not self not
through denying that which is self but
seeing it is fully dependent on this and
you fully understand it so lack of
understanding means putting this your
point of view first
lack of understanding not understanding
consciousness nervously
yeah let's not go into aggregates now
let's stick with the mindfulness but yes
it corresponds to the same thing
so my and mindfulness is always a move
or like something that I'm standing it's
just think it was something isn't it
it's just yeah uncle I have seen the
context it's been clouded by cutting the
right thing hers yeah that's what you
need to have knowledge in order for my
opinions to be right some of it always
comes first because if you don't know
what the context is
how can you recollect it how can you
discern it if the idea of mindfulness
for you is attending to my body here
right now means exactly that when I
don't attend to it my mindfulness is
gone because I the only mindfulness that
I know but if the mindfulness is based
on the sermon and the knowledge they
can't go because it's independent of
what you choose to attention all you
need to do is protect the context by not
contradicting the context you're acting
out of greed aversion delusion oh so
when you realize you've forgotten the
context you realized that forgetting is
included within it secondary good Indian
joining body I can't possibly have bee
hair having forgotten about my body if
there wasn't a body here yeah impossible
so doesn't matter
the extent of your forgetfulness the
extent of you remembering it if you have
understood the reference point correctly
it will be included properly which means
you cannot be forgetful and that is
going to be on the threshold that's
that's a college yeah that's always
stepping across the threshold of that
knowledge yeah and now you're partaking
the right - yeah so then even if you if
you got completely distracted with I
don't like to do something that require
like this full-on concentration when you
stop doing it your context is back
because you could have never left and
you understood that so with the context
really emerges so to speak you don't
mistake it you're not confused he
doesn't your confusion in regard to the
emerging context of your body being
there a necessary basis does not reduce
you to think your effect as when you
have gone beyond the doubt as well
and it's with Buddhist monks monks do
see this as a reason this is present do
you see this is manifested yes we do sir
do you see that on account of that being
manifested is the necessary basis this
comes to be as well says yes we do monks
the one who is not clear that this comes
first and this then comes second is the doubt
and this then comes second is the doubt
arising the mind yes it does because
they are not clear so it's just doubt
means confusion in regard to the right
order lapse of mindfulness means
confusion that we got to the right also
it means that you could still it's
possible fees is still as you when you
remember suddenly urine I realize you've
forgotten that's the body this still
remains a possibility for you to think
that that loss was because you weren't
paying attention to it in other words it
was you yeah exactly so I haven't
attended to hard enough hi I confessed
now that's it's really it's about
learning how to forget mindfully and not
preventing forgetfulness yeah and that's
the give him a learning jar described in
one of his talks when he was practicing
meditation he was all wound up trying to
concentrate his breath every second
every second and then he just you can't
sustain that and I said no but if I let
my mind think so you would let his mind
think and he would go further and go
further and keep a corner of a pond of
your I edit at the mind but inevitably
it will have to pass the point when you
forget and he will allow that to happen
as well and only stop it with that
forgetfulness would then carry on and
start thinking about lustful thoughts or
or grief and that's obvious that's
something you can also not be aware of
because it's all starts involving your
choice and that's when you okay now or
restart but not before that point but
usually people now restart every second
you restart for the sake of next
restarting and this for me like when I
kind of send me joke besides like
throwing an anchor but you don't wait to
be anchored you pull it an intro so your
purpose of anchoring is just to keep
chucking the anchor into
water and not let it angry so you want
to learn how to forget mindfully and
then you will not be able to lose the
context nor will you be able to kind of
drift into the sensuality near will and
distraction because that requires
choices that you make on account of the
doubt on account of the confusion
regarding the context not on account of
forgetfulness yeah because if you can't
accidentally sorry you can't
accidentally just unaware get and fully
engage with centrality or start start
harming somebody physically you it needs
to be on the level of choice that you
would make if the basis is muddled but
you with us a thousand say you wouldn't
you wouldn't make those choices if you
realize that no that necessary basis
comes first yeah you will you would be
impossible to make this any unwholesome
choice is always based on you trying to
control the feeling exactly exactly your
self a tell yourself first
I'm the master does every right to try
to control this yeah that's where
mindfulness you can't have too much of
it yeah because you are not doing it is
just recognition of Authority there and
they can be too much of it and that's
why restraint comes first
it's where strength comes first and
that's why I refer I'll hunt mindfulness
kabylia fullest and he doesn't need to
do it but he cannot not do it because
it's not about doing it anymore
his discernment is on that level so the
feeling that you have now is it
different so it's been like 15 minutes
and the same thing has been enduring at
the background and without you needing
to think about it so you realize see
even if you don't explicitly think of
that feeling comes first your point of
view comes second as a result of it your
attention you can say you already start
to discern that it comes first because
it was there independent of all of your
movements actions thoughts words you
said things you attended used the more
you you become familiar with exactly
it's that familiarity they want to
develop so when he goes away he doesn't
come back as a stranger yeah it's the
familiarity that thing that's always
been there yeah which means the whole
setup comes back with it
and that's also why all you need to do
once you're fully developed sensory
strength only to this practice
mindfulness and you won't be even
pressure personality anymore eventually
because see when you cannot provide the
order that is feeling or this body comes
first you cannot then give in to what
you want to attend as coming first which
is sense object so doesn't matter what
sense object comes your way you see it
within this context that's actually even
if I engage with sensuality this cannot
change and because of that you can't
forget it and because of that you can't
engage with it or with your will it
requires you to turn away from that
context but not just to ignore it but to
ignore it or the pretext of pretending I
am first-class I will still do what I
want to do and that's how you also get
to eventually understand that doesn't
matter the power and the extent of your
volition in your will this order can
change and that's when you abandon your
own choice the ownership of it so that
indirect recognition of the right order
but Pat yeah but you you can't make
choices which are based on it
killing someone sexual intercourse and
expect to maintain the right context ya
know cuz that requires the wrong order
yes that right order takes away the
passion exactly so much the extent of
the action that you just said the extent
of sexual intercourse the extent of
killing somebody these requires you
being first in your view in your in your
in your in a point of view putting that
first if you can why is it as a base can
you think because it's because basically
you're assuming that you have some level
of control over your feeling yeah and
it's that assumption of that control did
it basically did the extent of that
assumption yeah is required certain
extent for you to act physically yeah
either toward sensuality or towards
Somalian we may have the assumption
without acting exactly yeah which
t-swift so you need to stop acting
because you stop feeling the assumption
then you get to understand the
assumption and once it's adisyl it's
gone and then you cannot have like that
that's why that era hand is incapable of
sexual intercourse or intentional
killing not because those acts have lost
significance and he doesn't even know
what that is anymore no it's because he
cannot sort of twist his mind to the
extent necessary for those acts to be
intentionally done it's not it's not
also because he's got his kiss of all
that well power they know no just the
mind cannot be perverted to that extent
anymore it's just impossible
so yes alternatively then you can you
know if the feeling again when I say the
feeling usually it should be descend on
the level of the mood if you want to
practically start developing what we're
talking about but yeah you can do a body
so what is your kind of body posture so
whatever the body postures present means
the body needs to be there so you start
understanding necessity of the body
through their current body posture so
see again we be speaking for like half
an hour or something the mind was going
left to right explaining different
facets differently
your Porsche has remained unchanged and
you didn't have to attend to it and you
didn't have to keep telling to yourself
that you must be seen as it and you
forgot about you about the portion of
numerous amount of times yet the the
reference point of mindfulness is still
there so realize oh so it's really it's
how I remember it
if I remember it with that clarity with
the right context if I recognize it for
what it is that's how you maintain your
mindfulness not by having their kind of
you know the non lepsy mindfulness
people think the idea is you just hold
so tightly every second of your life for
the rest of your life one pen says yeah
no it's completely obvious it's just
you're unable to not recognize it yeah
you cannot mistake it anymore that's
what mindfulness is developed to the
extent necessary so I could focus on the
fact that my postures may be slightly
changed it's like your arms has changed
your a subjective change within the same
identity of the same seated position so
could you say if somebody if you notice
that you've suddenly in a different mood
hmm so what's in common to a good mood
was it comfortable I'm saying so it
tastes like make that move towards
including them okay included within
include the mood within the a greater
identity of the undulation thing which
makes it possible the mood to change
different things it'll be the same to be
a change yeah which makes possible which
makes it possible for a mood to change
yeah yeah if the current mood is the
utmost highest point of your mood it
could never change it would remain that
so good mood bad will neutral mood
what's in common to that it's a mood
it's not fine
so seated posture standing walking down
laying down what you counted but a body
we haven't having to be there so you get
to discern the identity of the
phenomenon of the enduring body through
being mindful of particular context of
your posture not through like I'm seeing
them seated up see nominees nominees and
you don't need to do that because you
already know where you are and what you
are and you the designation of seated
body or it is there because if I
are you seated now do you need to stop
and think about it and like stop body
sweeping from your toes to the top of
your head no you would know of course
I'm seated so just thinking so body
swing go through the body like this
involves basically just playing with
this image put it in playing with this
image I have of what my body looks like
spatially yeah based on the fact that I
know I'm saying though yeah I wouldn't
be possible if I didn't know they were
threat deeply dead results in you
putting the image of what you think the
body is first and not what the erection
here is which is the basis for that
image yeah yeah and that's why you
cannot be properly mindful yeah and you
can also stand it and that's why the
moment you forget about that image you
have forgot the only reference point in
you which was not even a reference point
it's like trying to try to anchor your
boat by throwing like the floating those
floating homes they just stay on the
surface of the water and then you float
with it yeah yeah anchored cuz you know
discerning through what's there so the
surface I see what I attend to and I
think that's what mindfulness is so I
already do is just keep touching the
surface so yeah it's just not saying the
necessary guys let's thank the only
reason you can attend to different parts
of your bodies cuz the body is already
there and you already know it because
when you are attending to your knees
you're not attending to your head but
attending to a head is a possibility in
the background of your attention which
is why you can then go and turn to it
and attend to the head but the sorry
already the nature of space is already a
nature of possibilities in different
directions and that's already within the
body being there that's why the entire
universe is contained within this body
less than 2 meters top as the Buddha
said it
so that's the whole point it's not like
when you sit to practice your meditation
or your mindfulness it's not about I
must stay mindful when I'm second oh I
must learn how to forget mindfully so
you want to allow yourself to forget and
then when you unforgettable induce
confusion about it if you do that's the
work that confusion needs to be
clarified yeah but I might like see even
if you're confused you don't need to try
to get rid of it you include it within
the body needing to be there thus you
doubt than any of the five hindrances
are then seen in the right light they're
secondary to the necessary base of the
body they don't give they don't have the
power over it if I'm putting yourself
first means putting the hindrances first
they become obstacles that's why the
hint exactly it seems to me that we just
getting this include including learning
how to include enhancing clear including
what including the context that remains
a change so the necessary basis for the
practice of including is discernment of
the context and that's what is I was
saying that maybe maybe not talk the
other day
oh maybe Oh somebody else when you know
like you hear this generic instruction
just come back to the present moment
just let go just let things go through
and it works for the day yeah okay
yeah because the problem of your
suffering is you resisting things and
now there's this novelty to tell you
don't resist and you don't resist it but
then your context of it still context of
resistance so then you start resisting
that and that's why you come back to the
present moment works initially helps you
with what I'm suffering but then oh now
you start doing that on account of
trying to avoid suffering you're not
including it so that's the danger and I
said you must include it people will
include it why why do you wanna include
it because you want to get rid of that
which bothers my point of view which
means my point of view is first and
needs dealing with these particular
things so you start doing mindfulness
correctly for the wrong reasons which
means it's not the right mind
you want to see that your point of view
second you have no say in it and if you
want oh my god that will overwhelm me
with anxiety and stuff in might which is
why you need to develop sensory strength
three sips unblemished virtue beforehand
Leonor of mug doesn't matter and pretty
much when you say the presence of
anxiety is possibly a good sign it is
it's a good symptom yeah yeah
because you're anxious only because you
don't know what to do yeah and then you
realize no that's the whole point it's
not about knowing what I must do it's
about knowing what I will not do yeah
and then you cannot be anxious being a
kite without knowing more exactly you
become okay which means you're not
anxious because you realize no I don't
know exactly what I won't do yeah that's
all I need to worry about I don't need
to worry about how would I figure this
out because I don't need failure yeah
the only reason why I needed to figure
it out is because I didn't know what I'm
not supposed to do
so then you mind drifts off then you
remember that your body is seated here
okay it's the same body is the same
position and the drifting there was a
way I don't need to use that as a yeah
what if what if what if no that was
within the body remaining unchanged all
this time even when I wasn't thinking
about but I wasn't practicing exactly so
you have this sense of duty sense of my
book this is what I must do even that
sense now you don't need to act out of
it you included in the body being
unchanged remaining in the same seated
position when you sat down to meditate
and that's how you stopped acting out of
doubt out of restlessness are the worry
out of remorse because you get to
descend the conflicts that's beyond it
the necessary basis for it and same boy
at the sensual thought had a sensual
thought within the context of the body
that hasn't been acting essentially yeah
that's what I said he would get to
understand these things because his
behavior has been purified beforehand
because the body has been factually not
engaging with these things anymore that
becomes your new container your new
reference point and that's how you get
to approach it on the level of the mind
eventually
three as the Buddha says knowing
thoughts of thoughts feelings experience
the body as the body your knowing clay I
have seen people they meditate and then
they feel like oh there was no more body
were no more thoughts I went beyond the
mind beyond the body
yeah it's true in the sense that they
went beyond what they think the body is
but there was a completely very very
limited perspective if you would get to
understand what the body as you do as
well it's impossible for for you to not
be there as a necessary base that's like
saying or the matter hit disappear half
of my aggregates were gone that's
inconceivable so just removing all the
wrong views and assumptions you would
have is that and that's the thing body
in the body everything I must attend to
the body within the body no means you've
seen the body within the body been
seeing the body with within whatever
particular is happening with the body
you still the nature of the body is
there so body within the body oh my body
seated my itching moving this that had
it within the body being there all these
things of the body that you can attend
impossible because the body is there all
these things within the feeling that you
can attend on account of feeling that
because feeling is there so feeling
within the feeling in other words
discerning the nature and not being sort
of gripped and losing the sight on
account of the particular thing that
pulled your attention like remaining
imperturbable in regard to discerning
the nature through that so you say it's
not it's not just seeing the nature but
seeing that any particular manifestation
of this thing is within is enclosed
within its subordinates who exactly
Jennifer yeah yeah exactly the
relationship between the nature and the
particular because if you're just
looking for the nature it can become the
new particular exactly and that's the
interpret it so but it's that
relationship it says with this this is space even if
it says with this this is space even if
you don't go into with what what is just
do this this is these two things are
present with this this has to be
with the particular there is the nature
there is the general there is of course
essence particular as you said it's the
first thing ya gets recognized through
which you discern the essence because of
which you realize that's why particulate
is there like the two sticks propping
each other yeah always so that's what
there is no ultimate Sankara you need to
discern or the ultimate nature the true
nature that underlies the entire
universe it's right here in this body
less than two meters - in your actions
in your speech in your thoughts it that
principle needs to be there and seeing
that will uproot a passion from all
these domains and that's all you need to
do why because seeing that it's these
two things that are mutually determining
each other leaves no room for the sense
of self the owner that's first
controlling them all yeah that depends
on that that depends on that if I look
at this I see this behind you
if I look at that I see this behind yeah
that's the same thing which means where
am I wherever I am I cannot be outside
of this dependence and that's when you
already stop practicing another now by
denying yourself but by including it in
the right order order that is dependable
upon these things they are not in your
control
to practice of mindfulness these
practice of mindful recollected
forgetfulness learning elsif learning
how to forget my ability without
inducing how to forget about that forget
learn how to forget without you're
forgetting inducing confusion and
ignorance and if it's induced you
included the necessary basis there was
necessary for your experience of
forgetting or learning how to forget in
the right order
yeah or not diverting the order to
unaccountable you know guess he'll
forget that yeah because it's actually
impossible to convert the order doesn't
matter really forget about it or not
being clear about it you stop being
wound up by your forgetting and equally
you stop acting out of passion when I
count of you're forgetting because you
won't be forgetting I'm forgetting that
just says the same lecture
anything else that it's an experience
that's right so I have experience of
forgetfulness on account of the present
body enduring here present feeling
enduring here which you cannot forget
like forgotten means it's gone it cannot
be gone and that's why it's in the
sphere of knowledge as we discussed that
before yeah you don't need to go around
thinking that two and two is four two
and two is four you know that always you
don't need to think about it it's there
because it's part of the level of
understanding now how to into work so
this you understand the order and you're
fully clear about the order it's in it
impossible to pervert the order through
the confusion about the understanding
means mindfulness is effortless and
that's the thing is that's the same
thing with two and sofas for you don't
keep meddling with it you don't have
this nervous sense that I've got to keep
going back to it I realize what the
steward here for it no matter what I do
it's a good thing I need to do so I'll
just stop doing any through the belt oh
because I don't think that's it whatever
you experience whatever you're meddling
with it's on account of the body being
there it's on account of the feelings in
you in there
I'm changing their identity
like they might be changing momentarily
while remaining the same feeling it's an
account of the mind being there on
account of the force being there
okay the boys are restless